<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr Culpeper's ghost, giving seasonable advice to the lovers of his writing. Before which is prefixed, Mris. Culpepers epistle in vindication of her husband's reputation</title>
            <author>Culpeper, Nicholas, 1616-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81149</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899875</idno>
  <idno type="VID">133244</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870445</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899875</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99899875e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2465:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr Culpeper's ghost, giving seasonable advice to the lovers of his writing. Before which is prefixed, Mris. Culpepers epistle in vindication of her husband's reputation</title>
                  <author>Culpeper, Nicholas, 1616-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Peter Cole, and are to be sold at his shop, at the sign of the Printing-Press in Corn-hil, neer the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Medicine --  Aphorisms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:1"/>
            <p>M<seg rend="sup">R</seg> CULPEPER'S GHOST, Giving Seasonable ADVICE to the LOVERS OF HIS WRITINGS.</p>
            <p>Before which is prefixed, Mris. Culpepers EPISTLE <hi>in</hi> Vindication <hi>of her Husband's</hi> Reputation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop, at the sign of the Printing-Press in Corn-hil, neer the Royal Exchange. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mris.</hi> Culpepers EPISTLE IN VINDICATION Of her Husbands REPUTATION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great are the Afflictions wherewith our <hi>Heavenly Father</hi> hath been pleased to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise me his poor <hi>Hand-maid,</hi> that I have not only lived to see my <hi>dear Husband,</hi> (the <hi>Stay</hi> and <hi>Solace</hi> of my Life) taken from me: but it hath been my hard hap also to see his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> and <hi>Memory</hi> (which will be dear to all Posterity, for the Works he hath written for the Common Good of this Nation) blemished, and Eclipsed, by the <hi>covetous</hi> and <hi>unjust Forgeries</hi> of one, Who, though he calls himself <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel,</hi> is far from being <hi>an Israelite in whom there is no guile;</hi> who was not content to publish a <hi>Hodg-podg</hi> of <hi>indigested Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections,</hi> and <hi>Observations</hi> of my dear Husband deceased, under the Title of <hi>Culpeper's last Legacy;</hi> but to make the Deceit more taking, he steeled his Forehead so far, and brased it so hard, as not to be ashamed to forge <hi>two Epistles,</hi> one in mine, and the other in my Husbands Name; of the penning of which, he nor I never so much as dream'd: And yet he <hi>impudently</hi> affirmeth in my Name, that my Husband <hi>Laid a severe Injunction on me to publish them for the general Good, after his decease; and
<pb facs="tcp:133244:3"/>that they are his last Experiences in Physick and Chyrurgery.</hi> And in the Title of his Book, he saith, <hi>They are the choycest, and most profitable Secrets, resolved never to be published till after his Death.</hi> All which Expressions in the Title and Epistles, are as false as the Father of Lyes; and every word in them, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and feigned. And he knew well enough, that no discreet, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man, that was a friend to my Husband, or me, would ever have agreed to such infamous and dishonest Practices; and therefore I desire all Courteous Readers of the Writings of my Husband, to take notice of this <hi>Deceit,</hi> and to assure themselves that it never entred into his head, to publish such an undigested <hi>Gallimoffery,</hi> under the promising and solemn Name of his <hi>Last Legacy,</hi> and that <hi>whereby he gained his Reputation in the World,</hi> as the Imposter makes him speak in his forged Epistle. And I desire any indifferent Reader, that hath observed my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands lofty, and Masculine manner of expressing himself in his Prefaces, and Epistles, Dedicatory, whether in case he had been minded or disposed to take so solemn a farewel of the world, as the <hi>Forger</hi> makes him to do; whether, <hi>I</hi> say, he would have done it in such a <hi>whining fashion,</hi> and so in the Stile of a <hi>Ballade-maker,</hi> as to say, <hi>And now, if it please Heaven to put a period to my Life, and Studies, that I must bid all things under the Sun farewel: Farewel to my dear Wife and Child, sarewel Arts and Sciences, farewel all worldly Glories, adieu Readers.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly my Husband would have been far more serious, and materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, in such a case, as any discreet man will judg. Neither can it be thought, that in such a solemn <hi>Valediction,</hi> he could possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly forget his wonted respects to the <hi>Colledg of Doctors,</hi> to whom he did so frequently address himself, in divers of his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteous Readers, I</hi> shall say no more touching the abuse of the Book-seller, only to prevent (as much as concerns me) thy being abused for the future, know, That my Husband left seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-nine Books of his own making, or Translating, in my hands, and "I have deposited them into the hands of his, and my much Honored Friend, Mr. <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> Book-seller, at the <hi>Printing-Press,</hi> neer the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> (for the good of my Child) from whom thou mayest expect to receive in Print, such of them as shall be thought fit to serve thee in due season, without any Disguises or Forgeries, unto which <hi>I</hi> do hereby give my attesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Also my Husband left seventeen Books compleatly perfected,
<pb facs="tcp:133244:3"/>in the hands of the said Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> for which he paid my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in his life-time: And Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> is ready and willing (on any good occasion) to shew any of the said seventy nine Books, or the seventeen, to such as doubt thereof.</p>
            <p>And if any Person shall question the Truth of any part of this Vindication, or Epistle; if they will take the pains to come to me, <hi>I</hi> will face to face, justifie the truth of every word thereof, as <hi>I</hi> have subscribed my Hand thereunto in the presence of many Witnesses.</p>
            <p>I profess in the Presence of the great God, the Searcher of all hearts, before whom Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> and I must one day give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all our Actions; That <hi>I</hi> have not published this Epistle or Vindication, out of any dis-respect to Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> (for <hi>I</hi> much respect the man, and would he glad to serve him to my power) but only to cleer my Husband from the folly and weakness cast up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by the means above expressed. And out of tenderness to Mr. <hi>Brooks, I</hi> first tried other means of keeping, and afterwards of repairing my Husbands Credit, and then stayed long to see if he would repair (in any measure) the wrong done to my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and my self. <hi>I</hi> desire to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Servant (in,<lb/> and for the Truth)</hi>
                  <lb/> Alice Culpeper.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my House,<lb/> next door to the<lb/> Red Lyon in<lb/> Spittle-fields,</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <date>October, <hi>18.<lb/> 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Mris. <hi>Culpeper</hi> did the 18. of <hi>October,</hi> subscribe this Epistle in Vindication of her Husband's <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> before Ten Witnesses, as she had done ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Epistle on the ninth of <hi>October,</hi> almost in the same words with this, except neer the Conclusion.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:4"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough that <hi>Ingenious</hi> and <hi>Active, Charitable</hi> Soul or <hi>Ghost</hi> of <hi>Dr. Culpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> hath left this <hi>World;</hi> yet <hi>Care</hi> of his <hi>Friends,</hi> and such as have been, or are his <hi>Schollers,</hi> (for being <hi>dead,</hi> he <hi>Teacheth</hi> in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-dying Monuments of his <hi>Learning, Wit, Industry,</hi> and <hi>Humanity;</hi> I mean his <hi>Writings</hi>) hath not left his <hi>Soul,</hi> as appears by this following Discourse. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any person brought it from the <hi>Elysian Fields</hi> (where it seems by this Relation, his <hi>Ghost</hi> at present is) or whether he delivered all this in an <hi>Apparition;</hi> or whether <hi>Spirits</hi> can write, and so he wrote it to some Friend of his, that will not be known, for fear he should be counted a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer,</hi> and one that had familiarity with <hi>Spirits?</hi> I will not determine. Perhaps
<pb facs="tcp:133244:4"/>his <hi>good Angel</hi> might receive it from him, and discover it to the <hi>Good Angel</hi> of his <hi>Wife,</hi> or <hi>Dr. Harrington,</hi> and the one or other of them, receiving it from their Tutelary <hi>Angel,</hi> might privately communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the same to some Friends for fear of the ill Speeches of <hi>People.</hi> However, being it hath been my good hap to get a Copy (though it may be, not so perfect as were to be wished, for the Connexion seems in some places faulty, and somtimes the Ghost speaks as to one, and other whiles as to many; somtimes as to a Messenger that should car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word to his Friends, and somtimes as if himself were present, speaking to them) I could not be so forgetful of my old Friend, and unfaithful to thee, whom I take to be his Friend, as to let it sleep in Oblivion, and miss of the good, <hi>that</hi> Charitable Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thee by it. Such a Comportance would not at all have become that Man, who is, and professeth himself to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Real Friend<lb/> to his Power,<lb/> PETER COLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:5"/>
            <head>The Names of Mr. <hi>Culpepers</hi> eight several Books of Physick, that thou art advised in this Discourse to buy.</head>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Practice of Physick,</hi> containing seventeen several Books. Wherein is plainly set forth, The <hi>Nature, Cause, Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences,</hi> and Several Sorts of <hi>Signs;</hi> Together with the <hi>Cure</hi> of all Diseases in the Body of Man. Being chiefly a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation of the <hi>The Works</hi> of that Learned and Renowned Doctor, <hi>Lazarus Riverius,</hi> Now living; Councellor and Physitian to the present King of <hi>France.</hi> Above fifteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of the said Books in Latin have been Sold in a very few Yeers, having been eight times printed, though al the former Impressions wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Nature, Causes, Signs,</hi> and <hi>Differences</hi> of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, and had only the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for the <hi>Cure</hi> of them; as plainly appears by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Epistle.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Anatomy of the Body of Man,</hi> Wherein is exactly described, the several parts of the Body of Man, illustrated with very many larger Brass Plates than ever was in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish before.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A Translation of the <hi>New Dispensatory,</hi> made by the Colledg of Physitians of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Whereunto is added, The <hi>Key to</hi> Galen's <hi>Method of Physick</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The <hi>English Physitian Enlarged;</hi> being an <hi>Astrologo-Physical</hi> Discourse of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Herbs of this Nation; wherein is shewed how to cure a mans self of most Diseases incident to Mans Body, with such things as grow in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and for three pence charge Also in the same Book is shewed, The time of gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al Herbs, both Vulgarly &amp; Astrologically. 2 The way of drying, and keeping them and their Juyces. 3 The way of making &amp; keeping al manner of useful Compounds, made of those Herbs.</p>
            <p n="5">5 A <hi>Directory for Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives,</hi> or a <hi>Guide for Women.</hi> Newly enlarged by the Author in every sheet, and Illustrated with divers new Plates.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Galen's</hi> Art of <hi>Physick,</hi> with a large Comment.</p>
            <p n="7">7 A <hi>New Method</hi> both of stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying and practising Physick.</p>
            <p n="8">8 A Treatise of the <hi>Rickets,</hi> being a Disease common to Children; wherein is shewed, 1 The Essence, 2 The Causes, 3 The Signs, 4 The Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Disease.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133244:5"/>
            <head>M<seg rend="sup">R</seg> CULPEPER'S GHOST, Giving Seasonable ADVICE to the LOVERS OF HIS WRITINGS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do most seriously and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Advise all my loving <hi>Friends,</hi> that accept kindly of my Labors and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, and delight in the <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> in their <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Tongue, that they would <hi>make Hay while the Sun shines,</hi> viz. Whiles the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a <hi>free Common-wealth</hi> last among them.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133244:6"/>For let them assure themselves, That (if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>God,</hi> for their <hi>Ʋnthankfulness,</hi> and <hi>Ʋnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Walking</hi> under his <hi>Mercies</hi>) shall cast again the <hi>Tyrannical Yoak</hi> of <hi>King-ship</hi> upon the <hi>Neck</hi> of the <hi>English Nation,</hi> they will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all those <hi>blessed Opportunities</hi> they now enjoy, to improve their Understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in this <hi>Art.</hi> For <hi>King-ship,</hi> (like the <hi>Devil</hi> cast out) will returning, bring SEVEN DEVILS worse than it self, and the <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> of the Nation will be worse than ever, and ten-fold more <hi>Aegyptian.</hi> And as the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>King-ship</hi> hath alwaies been, and ever will be, attended with a <hi>Luxurious</hi> and <hi>debauched Court;</hi> so will the <hi>Debaucheries</hi> be encreased <hi>seven fold</hi> by the Instigation of those <hi>seven</hi> other <hi>Devils.</hi> And then <hi>(Friends)</hi> the prime <hi>Factors</hi> of <hi>Physick,</hi> of the <hi>Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing upstart London Colledg,</hi> will be called to secret <hi>Court-Ministries,</hi> and to be of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet Council</hi> of some <hi>Court-Nimrods,</hi> sick of such Diseases that punish, as well by the <hi>shame,</hi> as <hi>pain</hi> which attends them. Then will the <hi>Factors</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> so employed, dare without much <hi>blushing</hi> to beseech their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched</hi> and <hi>Frenchified</hi> Lordships, to become earnest Solicitors to the <hi>Kings most Excellent Majestie;</hi> that for the <hi>Profit</hi> of his Majesties Realms, undone by <hi>Knowledg,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133244:6"/>the <hi>Gain</hi> of the <hi>Colledg Factors,</hi> that they may be able to attend the <hi>Court,</hi> when called, in a <hi>splendid Equipage;</hi> and as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneration of their <hi>Fidelity</hi> and secrecy in their <hi>Court Services;</hi> That all <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> in the <hi>English</hi> Tongue, may by express and speedy Order of his most excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, be burnt by the Hand of the <hi>Hang-man</hi> at the usual places of such <hi>Martyrdoms,</hi> but especially at the Royal Exchange, over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Pestilent Peters</hi> own Shop; and that al Persons be enjoyned from City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to bring in all their <hi>Physick Books</hi> to the <hi>Colledg</hi> at <hi>Amen-Corner;</hi> and that all <hi>Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, Countrie Practitioners, Apothecaries, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> and <hi>Ladies,</hi> may be strictly enjoyned under a severe Penalty to be expressed, to blot out of their <hi>Remembrance</hi> all the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of <hi>Physick</hi> gained from such Books, and never to think thereof, so much as in a Dream; and that all sick Persons may be enjoyned from all Parts of the Nation, and from aboord the Ships of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> to repair in Person, or by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, with their Waters, to the <hi>Colledg of London</hi> for Physick, just as they do to <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster for Law</hi> (for if his Majesty please, they may do one as well as the other) and that it may be a <hi>Star Chamber</hi> Case, for any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133244:7"/>man to print and publish such Books, or to read and inform themselves thereby.</p>
            <p>Now their <hi>Lordships</hi> must be Judges in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> and they will be zealous in this Cause so neerly concerning their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Friends, the <hi>Colledg Factors,</hi> who had lately healed them from those <hi>Brandmarks</hi> made with a BURNING-HOT-MISTRIS, which they received by Sentence given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their <hi>Lordships</hi> in the Court of <hi>Sun-Chamber</hi> in Heaven; not upon their <hi>Cheeks, Foreheads,</hi> or <hi>Ears,</hi> where their Lordships were wont to brand men, but upon their PRIAPEIAN UTENSILES, for the sweet Sin of <hi>Lechery,</hi> the Fruit of their <hi>Tyrannical Pride</hi> and <hi>Luxurie.</hi> Think <hi>(Friends)</hi> how the poor Printers, and Publishers of <hi>Physick Books</hi> in the <hi>English Tongue,</hi> wil be Sentenced by their <hi>Frenchified Lordships,</hi> assure your selves the Censures of <hi>Laton, Prin, Bastwick,</hi> and <hi>Burton,</hi> were but Fleabitings to the Penalties that shal be decreed by that <hi>High Court,</hi> against such heinous offenders against the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of the <hi>Colledg.</hi> A word to the wise is sufficient, Buy these
<note n="*" place="margin">The Names of the Books I advise you to buy, thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est find after the end of the Epistle to this Discourse.</note>
               <hi>Books</hi> while you can get them, study them wel, and keep them warily when you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133244:7"/>have them, and by this means you wil cause more to be published in this kind, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by great dispersion of <hi>Copies</hi> far &amp; wide transmit this knowledg to al your posterity, <hi>Maugre</hi> the <hi>Beards</hi> of al future <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and their <hi>Factors</hi> of <hi>Physick.</hi> And I would have my Country-men to be very thankful to <hi>Almighty God</hi> for the present <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and to pray continually for their <hi>Sober, Honest,</hi> and <hi>Generous Governors,</hi> that care not to oblige any <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Fraternity</hi> of men, by <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>wicked Acts,</hi> which highly disoblige the <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> And (Freinds) if any of the <hi>Colledg</hi> cry down the <hi>Authors</hi> by me Published, and I hear some are so impudent as to disparage <hi>Rive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> (which is al one, as if a <hi>Civilian</hi> should through dirt in the Face of <hi>Justinian</hi>) Laugh at them and Pity them (for it is the last Game they have to play) but beleeve them not; know rather assuredly, that in the Books by me composed or translated, the principal of which is the renowned <hi>Riverius</hi> (since my unbodying, compleatly publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed) there are the best <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> in a <hi>Galenical</hi> way that are, or ever wil be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, for we know what those <hi>Principles</hi> can produce. And as for <hi>Chymistry,</hi> of which <hi>I</hi> had a mighty high opinion in my Life
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133244:8"/>time: I must confess, though I stil acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Art to be very ingenious and use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to search into the Misteries of Nature, and the best key of <hi>Natural Philosophy,</hi> &amp; that by help thereof some very useful Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are daily made, as my <hi>Aurum Potabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> of which I left a Treatise; yet I do now much doubt whether a General supply of Medicaments for al Cases obvious in Practice, can by <hi>Chymistrie</hi> be afforded bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the often-approved and by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence confirmed <hi>Galenical</hi> and <hi>Hyppocratical</hi> Remedies. The occasion that made me first incline to this opinion, was thus. I met here in the <hi>Elysian Fields</hi> accidentally with <hi>Factor Wright junior,</hi> who first lived with <hi>Doctor Flud</hi> in <hi>Fan-church street,</hi> being a Youth and gave out his Physick (as his <hi>House-Apothecary</hi>) who told me that his Mr. <hi>Flud,</hi> though a <hi>Trismegistian-Platonick-Rosy-crucian Doctor,</hi> gave his Patients the same kind of <hi>Galenical Medicaments,</hi> which other Physitians in the Town ordinarily appointed, and when himself was sick, he had no Chymical <hi>Elixars</hi> or <hi>Quintessential Extracts</hi> to relie upon, but after he had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed himself to be let blood (an ordinary <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenical</hi> Remedy) he sent for <hi>Doctor Gulstone,</hi> &amp; relied upon his advise for the Cure of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133244:8"/>disease, who was a <hi>pure Galenist.</hi> And I wel remember in one of his Folio Books treating of Preservation of Health, his only Physick he recommends, is a <hi>Mastich Pill,</hi> with a drop of <hi>Oyl of Time,</hi> than which the Apothecaries Shop knows no more common Medicine. And therefore he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so great, and so sublime a <hi>Doctor,</hi> as to have written many Volums in Folio, full of <hi>Mathematical, Mystagogical, Chymical-Rosicruce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Speculations,</hi> which Books are highly esteemed by many beyond Seas, and by some at home: If all his Skill in <hi>Chymistry</hi> (of which the <hi>Rosie-Crucian Seraphical illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Fraternity,</hi> are the chief Masters) or other Mysterious Arts, had furnished him with any more effectual Medicaments than the <hi>Galenical,</hi> such as are in the <hi>London Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensatory,</hi> I cannot doubt but he would have used them, if not for Conscience sake, yet for to advance his Reputation, by the <hi>quickness, safeness,</hi> and <hi>pleasantness</hi> of the Cure, which is that the <hi>Chymists</hi> boast of. After the foresaid Relation of <hi>Factor Wright Junior,</hi> I happened to meet with <hi>Old Dr. Flud,</hi> walking very musefully, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Ghosts of <hi>Raimundus Lullius,</hi> and <hi>Van Helmont;</hi> I took old Dr. <hi>Flud</hi> aside, and asked him if the Relation of his Servant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133244:9"/>
               <hi>Robert Wright</hi> were true. Hereupon the old man ingenuously confessed the thing, and said there were no better Medicaments in the whol world than the Galenical; and so left me to return to his Company, they being (as I over heard) in a great Dispute about the <hi>Weapon-Salve,</hi> and plotting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about a rare Invention, <hi>viz.</hi> How to invent an <hi>Ʋniversal Magnetick Medicine</hi> for Feavers, which being put into the <hi>Ʋrine</hi> of a <hi>sick Patient,</hi> the quantity of a few drops, should <hi>Sympathetically</hi> work the same Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Cure of the Feaver, as the <hi>Weapon-salve</hi> being anointed upon the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, does upon the wound. For Dr. <hi>Flud</hi> said, if the <hi>Spirits</hi> in the <hi>Blood</hi> sticking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sword, when it is anointed, do by Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy fly unto the Body whence they came, and carry along with them the vertue of the Salve, as I have cleerly demonstrated in my Book against <hi>Hoplocrisma-spongos,</hi> or my <hi>Squeezing of Parson</hi> Fosters <hi>Spunge:</hi> why may not the vertues of a <hi>Magnetick Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> dropped into the Patients Urine, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Urine remaining warm, be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the inmost Bowels of the Body, especially the <hi>Liver, Spleen, Kidneys,</hi> and <hi>Bladder,</hi> by the Spirits of those parts which came away in the <hi>Ʋrine,</hi> and when the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133244:9"/>
               <hi>Ʋrine</hi> becomes cold, do retire into the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whence they came, by a <hi>Vertual Attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> caused by the <hi>Emanation</hi> of the <hi>invisible Atomes</hi> that come from those parts in the sick Body, through the air into the chamber-pot or Urinal, to visit their fellow Spirits there imprisoned. Truly (replyed <hi>Van Helmont</hi>) this may very well be done; for the <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative Odor</hi> of the <hi>Gas Aquae</hi> in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Blas Meteoron,</hi> impregnated with the <hi>Magnum Oportet,</hi> which lies ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetted in the <hi>Centre</hi> of the <hi>Magnetick Spirit,</hi> dropped into the Urine, may in a moment, and like Lightening, penetrate the <hi>sick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,</hi> and meeting with the <hi>Faber Archeus</hi> (who is now so inraged, and blows his Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows with such Bedlam fury, that al his shop is afire about his Ears) so charm and pacifie him, and pierce into the <hi>Individual punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of his Central Essence,</hi> so tickle him (as men are wont to tickle the Trouts, and other Fish, when they intend with their hands to throw them out of the Water) that he shall become as gentle as a Lamb, and recovering his wits, quench the fire he hath made, and put all in Tune again. This was the Discourse of these three <hi>Chymical Grandees,</hi> but they could not well agree; for <hi>Raimundus Lullius,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Flud</hi> varied from <hi>Min Heere Van Helmont</hi> (who said they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133244:10"/>were not <hi>Adepti</hi>) so that they agreed to chuse Arbitrators; <hi>Raimund</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> chose <hi>Trismegistus,</hi> and <hi>John Baptist</hi> chose <hi>Paracelsus:</hi> But what was the Conclusion of this Consult, I have not yet learned. And so farewel. Hola! Doest thou hear Friend, I will tell thee a Tale before thou go, which will confirm what I formerly said. Word is newly come to the <hi>Elysian Fields,</hi> that a Learned <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Factor of Physick,</hi> independent upon the <hi>Colledg</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> was lately dealt with by a Pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Colledg Factor,</hi> who would needs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade him to come into the <hi>Colledg.</hi> But the said <hi>Independent Factor,</hi> said to the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterian,</hi> or <hi>Colledg Factor,</hi> That he knew no reason why he should desire to be of the <hi>Colledg,</hi> but divers against it, as loss of his <hi>Liberty</hi> in many respects, and being subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and made inferior to those that are his Inferiors in <hi>standing</hi> in the <hi>Ʋniversity,</hi> and perhaps in all other things save <hi>Mounteban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kry,</hi> &amp;c. subjoyning, that to seek a thing out of <hi>design of advancing a Mans self,</hi> which will <hi>really debase</hi> him, is the greatest <hi>Folly</hi> in the world. To which the <hi>Presbiterian,</hi> or <hi>Colledg Factor</hi> answered, You had best for al that joyn your self to the <hi>Colledg,</hi> because YOU KNOW NOT WHAT TIMES
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133244:10"/>ARE COMING: Intimating that he the said <hi>Colledg Factor,</hi> hath hopes that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tyranny</hi> shall be restored, and that the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal and Tyrannical <hi>Ʋsurpation</hi> of the <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polizing Colledg</hi> (who since the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> hath been established in opposition to <hi>King-ship,</hi> have drawn in their <hi>Horns</hi>) shall again flourish, and <hi>play Rex,</hi> as in daies of old, when they had the <hi>Impudence</hi> to afflict by <hi>Imprisonment,</hi> and other waies, men as <hi>well Educated,</hi> and as <hi>Learned</hi> as themselves (contrary to their Charter, which gives them no power derogating from, and disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling the ancient Priviledg of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and other Universities, which Authorize men to Practice in all Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) because they would not bow the Knee to <hi>Haman</hi> that sate in the Kings Gate, nor submit themselves and <hi>the Dignity of the Ʋniversities</hi> to the <hi>Monopolizing Conventicle</hi> at <hi>Amen Corner,</hi> so as to become their Subjects, and Vassels to their Usurped Prerogative. And since <hi>that,</hi> a <hi>Reverend old Colledg Factor</hi> who by <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Physick &amp;c.</hi> hath scraped together a BARONS <hi>Estate,</hi> &amp; may likely be a <hi>Star-chamber Lord,</hi> when the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> is restored, told one that brought an English Physick Book to him to <hi>Licence,</hi> that he would neither <hi>Approve</hi> nor <hi>Licence</hi> it, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133244:11"/>THE TIME WAS COMING, THAT A COURSE SHOULD BE TAKEN A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST AL SUCH BOOKS AS THOSE. Remember this story <hi>Country men,</hi> and pray for the Continuance of your <hi>Liberties</hi> and the <hi>just Mannagers</hi> of the same, for with the revival and reduction of <hi>Kingly Tyranny,</hi> by a necessary and Natural consequence, <hi>Lords Tyranny, Bishops Tyranny, Star-chamber Tyranny, Courts of Honor</hi> and of <hi>Amen Corner &amp;c.</hi> wil revive and shew themselves as <hi>Brisk</hi> as <hi>Body-Lice.</hi> Farewel.</p>
            <p>Hola! one word more. Good honest freind commend me heartily to the <hi>Author</hi> of that <hi>Epigram</hi> Printed with <hi>Riverius,</hi> at the end of his <hi>Epistle,</hi> and thank him for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming me what a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> is <hi>indeed</hi> and <hi>intruth,</hi> and what a <hi>meer Factor</hi> of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick. I confess I never considered how that FACERE MEDICINAM is to practice <hi>Physick;</hi> and DOCTOR and QUI DOCET are <hi>Convertible</hi> terms of the same <hi>Synonymal</hi> import: and that a Man can be no more a <hi>Doctor</hi> without <hi>Disciples</hi> or <hi>Scholars</hi> then a <hi>Father</hi> without <hi>Children,</hi> a <hi>Master</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Servants,</hi> or a <hi>Prince</hi> without <hi>Subjects.</hi> Whereas he that teaches any Art is a <hi>Doctor</hi> of that Art in spight of al that al the <hi>Colledges</hi> in the world shal be able so say or do to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133244:11"/>daies of <hi>Eternity,</hi> unless they can bereave men of their <hi>understandings,</hi> and change the <hi>common Speech</hi> of <hi>Man-kind.</hi> So that a Man may be a <hi>Doctor</hi> or <hi>Teacher</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> and no <hi>Factor</hi> or Practiser; or a <hi>Practiser,</hi> or <hi>Factor</hi> (which is the true word) and no <hi>Teacher</hi> thereof; or he may be both a <hi>Teacher and Factor,</hi> as I was when <hi>I</hi> lived in the <hi>Body.</hi> And verily it is a most ridiculous thing, that he which intends onely to Practise the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Healing,</hi> should not think himself quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thereunto until with much <hi>Labor</hi> and <hi>expence</hi> he has purchased the idle name of a <hi>Teacher</hi> of Physick: as if a <hi>Barrister</hi> or <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler</hi> at Law, should not think himself fitly qualified to plead at the <hi>Bar,</hi> unless he should with great travil and expence at <hi>Court</hi> procure himself the <hi>Empty name</hi> of a <hi>Judg,</hi> or a <hi>Doctor of the Laws of England.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess <hi>I</hi> am fully inlightened and convinced in this point, and if I were to live again in your world, I would write my self <hi>Doctor of Physick</hi> instead of <hi>Nich. Culpeper,</hi> Gent. For besides al the <hi>Reason</hi> in the world on my side (for I dare say <hi>I</hi> have been a greater <hi>Teacher</hi> of <hi>Physick,</hi> and have had incomparably more <hi>Disciples</hi> in that <hi>Art,</hi> than al the <hi>Fellows</hi> of <hi>Amen Colledg</hi> since old King Harry gave them their Charter (which in al probability dropt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133244:12"/>out of his great <hi>Codpiece</hi>) not foreseeing what ill use they would make of it) <hi>I</hi> would justifie my self by the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Doctor John Collins,</hi> the <hi>Kings Professor</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg,</hi> who in his Commendato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Epigram to <hi>Mr. Ralph Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who Versified <hi>Hippocrates</hi> Aphorismes in <hi>Greek Verses,</hi> thus
<note n="*" place="margin">At the end of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> Aphorisms in Greek and Latin Verse, printed at <hi>Cambridg.</hi>
               </note> speaks.
<q>
                  <l>Non <hi>Toga, Pileolús</hi> ve, nec <hi>Oscula, Dactylius</hi> ve</l>
                  <l>Verè <hi>Doctorem,</hi> néve <hi>Cathedra</hi> facit:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Doct<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ris</hi> quamvis hec sint <hi>Insignia</hi> facti.</l>
                  <l>His sine, <hi>Doctorem</hi> te facit ipse <hi>Liber.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor</hi> Gown, <hi>nor</hi> Cap, <hi>nor</hi> Kiss, <hi>nor</hi> Golden Ring</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor</hi> Chair <hi>a</hi> Doctor <hi>makes, nor no such thing.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>These may</hi> adorn, <hi>but can no</hi> Doctor <hi>make,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Without al which thou for thy</hi> Poems <hi>sake</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Doctor <hi>art.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And if <hi>Ralph Winterton</hi> who then had no other university degree then of a <hi>Master</hi> of <hi>Arts</hi> was by the Kings <hi>professor</hi> of Physick pronounced a <hi>Doctor</hi> of Physick, the said <hi>Professor</hi> acknowledging that his <hi>Book</hi> had made him so, which notwithstanding was no more than an ingenious turning of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates
<pb facs="tcp:133244:12"/>Aphorisms</hi> into <hi>Greek</hi> verse, whereby the <hi>sence</hi> indeed of the Author was <hi>illustrated</hi> and made more intelligible: who shal deny me to have been a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Physick,</hi> that have not only <hi>translated</hi> but <hi>composed</hi> divers <hi>Books</hi> of my own, to <hi>teach</hi> the said <hi>Art.</hi> So that I could wish that <hi>Peter Cole</hi> would here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after Print me NICH. CULPEPER DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTOR OF PHYSICK and leave out GENT. For al the world must needs of themselves know that a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> is a <hi>Gentleman</hi> in the <hi>Superlative</hi> Degree.</p>
            <p>So farwel. Commendations to my <hi>Wife</hi> and my noble freind <hi>Factor Harrington,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> desire to be good unto my <hi>Wife</hi> and to supply my <hi>Absence</hi> as much as he possibly can. Commendations also to al freinds and honest <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Factors</hi> of <hi>Physick,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious <hi>Book-sellers,</hi> saving him that abused me by Printing my Notes (partly collected in the Infancy of my studies, but many of them with an intent to refute the same, some of which refutations I did Print) under the name of <hi>Culpepers last Legacie of rare secrets &amp;c.</hi> whereby he makes me contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict my self in my own writings (To the hazard of the Lives of many of the good people of this Nation) which is the highest Injurie can be done to a Man. If he leave
<pb facs="tcp:133244:13"/>not off such <hi>tricks,</hi> I would advise him to pul down the sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> and hang up the <hi>Devil,</hi> or the sign of his <hi>Cloven foot,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead thereof: that people may Guess by the sign what <hi>Commodities</hi> he deals in, and Know where to have them, without seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further about the Town. For when they see the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Lies</hi> and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, or his MITRED <hi>Foot</hi> hang up, <hi>they</hi> may be sure that love <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Sophisticated Forgeries</hi> (as too many do) where to have their turn served. VALE.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:133244:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>